# Dr. rer. nat. Martin Bies

# Curriculum Vitae



RPTU Kaiserslautern-Landau
Department of Mathematics
Gottlieb-Daimler-Straße 48 (Office 433)
67663 Kaiserslautern, Germany
December 15, 1987 (Merzig, Germany)
Single (Not Married)
+49 (0)631 205 2850
martin.bies@rptu.de
https://martinbies.github.io/

German
Native
English
Full Proficiency
French
Modest (CEFR Level B1)

#### **SUMMARY**

I hold a **PhD in Physics** (*Heidelberg Univ.*, 2018), specializing in **string theory** and **mathematics**. My research is inspired by **computational analysis** of **massless spectra in string vacua**, resulting in publications on **toric geometry**, **Freyd categories**, **Brill-Noether theory**, and **root bundles**. Proficient in *julia*, C++, and *python*, I excel in **open-source software development** (*git*) to advance **computational research**. My diverse expertise emphasizes my interdisciplinary commitment. With a history of **international collaborations**, full **English proficiency**, and extensive **teaching experience**, I showcase a versatile skill set.

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

CURRENT, FROM IO/2022 (FT)

# Mathematics Dept., RPTU Kaiserslautern-Landau, GER *Research Associate*

I enhance the toric geometry capabilities and develop advanced algebraic geometry tools for string theory geometries within the OSCAR computer algebra system (oscar-system.org). Funded by the SFB-TRR 195 – Symbolic Tools in Mathematics and their Application, I added/modified 160,000+ lines of code.

09/202I - 08/2022 (FT)

Dept. of Phys. & Astron., University of Pennsylvania, USA *Simons Postdoctoral Fellow* 

Continuation of Simons Foundation project.

09/2020 - 08/202I (FT)

Dept. of Mathematics, University of Pennsylvania, USA Simons Postdoctoral Fellow

Work with M. Cvetič and R. Donagi on root bundles and the F-theory QSMs (funded by the *Simons Foundation*).

10/2019 - 09/2020 (FT)

Mathematical Institute, University of Oxford, UK *Long Term Visitor* 

Continuation of Wiener-Anspach project initiated at PTM, Brussels.

10/2018 - 09/2019 (FT)

PTM, Université Libre de Bruxelles, BE

Postdoctoral Researcher

M/F-Theory: Engineering Of Super Conformal Field Theories (funded by the *Foundation Wiener-Anspach*).

## ITP, Heidelberg University, GER

#### Research Associate

AI-tools meet jumps in vector-like spectra (preparation of Cluster of Excellence EXC 2181 STRUCTURES).

#### **EDUCATION**

03/2014 - 02/2018 PhD in Physics (Grade: Magna Cum Laude)

ADVISOR: PROF. T. WEIGAND (PHYSICS) & PROF. M. BARAKAT (MATHEMATICS)

Heidelberg University, GER

09/2012 - 02/2014 Master of Physics (Grade: 1.0)

ADVISOR: PROF. T. WEIGAND Heidelberg University, GER

10/2010 - 06/2011 ERASMUS exchange student

Imperial College, London

10/2008 - 08/2012 Bachelor of Physics (Grade: 1.1)

ADVISOR: PROF. T. WEIGAND Heidelberg University, GER

#### SCHOLARSHIPS AND AWARDS

04/2024 - CURRENT TU-Nachwuchsring

Funding: 3000€.

Status: M. Mikelsons (BSc. Mathematics) hired as research assistant.

Goal: Enhance the OSCAR computer algebra system (oscar-system.org),

focusing on the FTheoryTools module, and utilize it for research.

01/2010 - 02/2018 Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes

2014: Awarded PhD scholarship.

2010: Awarded Bachelor and Master scholarship.

10/2010 – 06/2011 ERASMUS scholarship

#### RECENT COLLABORATIONS

FROM 2022 FTheoryTools in OSCAR

Initiated with **A. P. Turner** (*University of Pennsylvania, USA*).

Later joined by M. Zach (RPTU KL-LD, GER), Prof. Frühbis-Krüger (Univ. Oldenburg, GER).

Goal: In OSCAR, create computer tools for string theory (in particular F-theory) applications.

Key features: Crepant singularity resolution and database of existing constructions. Status: First paper expected by end-2024, paving way for cutting-edge applications.

From 04/2024: Hired research Assistant M. Mikelisons (funded by *TU-Nachwuchsring*).

FROM 2021 Toric Geometry in OSCAR

Together with **L. Kastner** (Technische Universitaet Berlin, GER).

Goal: Solid foundation of toric geometry in OSCAR and integration with Polymake.

Status: **S. Telen**'s (MPI-MiS Leipzig, GER) lecture used OSCAR's toric geometry: arxiv-2203.01690.

An overview over the provided functionality is available in *Computer Algebra Rundbrief*.

**G. Muratore**'s (Univ. de Lisboa, PRT) article arxiv-2309.03741 is based on our work.

A dedicated chapter of the OSCAR book will detail further updates, due in fall 2024.

Applications of Root Bundles to F-theory Standard Models FROM 2020

> Collaboration with **Prof. M. Cvetič** and **Prof. R. Donagi** (*University of Pennsylvania, USA*). Initially, contributions from **M. Liu** (back then, PhD student at *University of Pennsylvania, USA*). Continued work with **M. Ong** (PhD student at *University of Pennsylvania, USA*).

Goal: Explore creating a single Higgs field in F-theory standard models using root bundles.

Status: Resulted in 5 peer-reviewed papers (#1, #2, #3, #4, #5 of my publications).

## **SERVICES**

07/2024	Organizing session at conference <i>ICMS 2024</i> (together with M. Zach & L. Kastner).
02/2024	Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes: Member of the admission board – virtual event via zoom.
FALL 2023	Expert at European Commission: Accessment of research proposals in Mathematics and Physics.
SINCE 2021	10+ letters of recommendation.
06/2018	Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes: Member of the admission board Heidelberg.
12/2017	Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes: Member of the admission board Ellwangen III.
05/2017	Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes: Training for admission board members – successfully completed.
11/2016	Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes: Member of the admission board Heidelberg.

## OTHER TRAININGS

03/2024	Moderation of meetings and project discussions (Kaiserslautern, GER). Offered by: <i>TU Nachwuchsring</i>
05/2018	Kontaktseminar – Schwerpunkt Banken und Beratung (Bonn, GER) Offered by: <i>Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes</i>
05/2018	Physiker im Beruf (Bad Honnef, GER) Offered by: Deutsche Physikalische Gesellschaft (DPG)

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

```
0000-0002-9609-1693
                   ORCID
                          57197835420
                 SCOPUS
                           5 (Based on peer-reviewed works, only.)
                H-INDEX
    TOTAL PUBLICATIONS
PEER REVIEWED/ACCEPTED
          UNDER REVIEW
              OUTREACH
           UNPUBLISHED
                  THESIS
              JOUR NALS
                          Journal of High Energy Physics (5)
                          Journal of Algebra and Its Applications (1)
                           Physical Review D (1)
                           Proceedings of Symposia in Pure Mathematics (AMS) (1)
                           Communications In Mathematical Physics (1)
```

#### Peer Reviewed Publications

- M. Bies, M. Cvetič, R. Donagi, M. Ong, *Improved Statistics for F-theory Standard Models*, Preprint: https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.02535, Jul. 2023, accepted by *Communications in Mathematical Physics* and being prepared for printing.
- M. Bies, Root bundles: Applications to F-theory Standard Models, in String-Math 2022, R. Donagi, A. Langer, P. Sułkowski, and K. Wendland, eds., Proceedings of Symposia in Pure Mathematics, vol. 107, American Mathematical Society, 2024, pp. 17–43. ISBN: 978-1-4704-7240-5. DOI: 10.1090/pspum/107. (A preprint is available at arXiv:2303.08144.)
- 3 M. Bies, M. Cvetič, R. Donagi, M. Ong, Brill-Noether-general Limit Root Bundles: Absence of vector-like Exotics in F-theory Standard Models, Journal of High Energy Physics, Nov. 2022, DOI: 10.1007/JHEP11(2022)004.
- **M. Bies**, M. Cvetič, M. Liu, *Statistics of Root Bundles Relevant for Exact Matter Spectra of F-theory MSSMs*, Physical Review D, Sept. 2021, DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevD.104.L061903.
- 5 M. Bies, M. Cvetič, R. Donagi, M. Liu, M. Ong, Root Bundles and Towards Exact Matter Spectra of Ftheory MSSMs, Journal of High Energy Physics, Sept. 2021, DOI: 10.1007/JHEP09(2021)076
- 6 **M. Bies**, S. Posur, *Tensor Products of Finitely Presented Functors*, Journal of Algebra and Its Applications, July. 2021, DOI: 10.1142/s0219498822501869.
- 7 M. Bies, M. Cvetič, R. Donagi, L. Ling, M. Liu, F. Ruehle, *Machine Learning and Algebraic Approaches towards Complete Matter Spectra in 4d F-theory*, Journal of High Energy Physics, Jan. 2021, DOI: 10.1007/JHEP01(2021)196.
- 8 M. Bies, C. Mayrhofer, T. Weigand, Algebraic Cycles and Local Anomalies in F-theory, Journal of High Energy Physics, Nov. 2017, DOI: 10.1007/jhep11(2017)100.
- 9 M. Bies, C. Mayrhofer, T. Weigand, Gauge Backgrounds and Zero-Mode Counting in F-theory, Journal of High Energy Physics, Nov. 2017, DOI: 10.1007/jhep11(2017)081.

#### Outreach

- M. Bies, A. P. Turner, F-Theory Applications, in The Computer Algebra System OSCAR: Algorithms and Examples, W. Decker, C. Eder, C. Fieker, M. Horn, and M. Joswig, eds., Algorithms and Computation in Mathematics, vol. 32, Springer, 1st ed., to appear by end of 2024, pp. 453–475. ISSN: 1431-1550.
- M. Bies, L. Kastner, *Toric Geometry*, in *The Computer Algebra System OSCAR: Algorithms and Examples*, W. Decker, C. Eder, C. Fieker, M. Horn, and M. Joswig, eds., Algorithms and Computation in Mathematics, vol. 32, Springer, 1st ed., to appear by end of 2024, pp. 193–213. ISSN: 1431-1550.
- M. Bies, L. Kastner, *Toric Geometry in OSCAR*, ComputerAlgebraRundbrief 72 (03/2023), 20-25, Mar. 2023, Preprint: https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08110.

## Unpublished Works

13 **M. Bies**, C. Mayrhofer, C. Pehle, T. Weigand, *Chow Groups, Deligne Cohomology and Massless Matter in F-theory*, Feb. 2014, https://arxiv.org/abs/1402.5144.

#### Thesis

- M. Bies, Cohomologies of Coherent Sheaves and Massless Spectra in F-theory, PhD thesis, Heidelberg university, Feb. 2018, Heidelberg University Library, available at DOI: 10.11588/HEIDOK.00024045.
- 15 **M. Bies**, Cohomologies of holomorphic line bundles in smooth and compact normal toric varieties, MSc. thesis, Heidelberg university, February 2014, available on author's academic homepage.
- 16 **M. Bies**, Intersecting D6-brane models on  $T^2 \times T^2 \times T^2 / (\sigma \times \Omega)$  and  $T^2 \times T^2 \times T^2 / (\mathbb{Z}_2 \times \mathbb{Z}_2 \times \sigma \times \Omega)$  orientifolds, BSc. thesis, Heidelberg university, August 2012, available on author's academic homepage.

## TALKS, POSTERS, CONFERENCES

#### Organizer of Conference (1)

07/2024 Session at ICMS 2024 (Durham, UK)

#### Invited Talks (8)

- 07/2023 Third Annual Meeting 2023 of SFB-TRR 195 (Saarbruecken, GER)
  Title: F-Theory: Exemplifying OSCAR's Pursuit for Multidisciplinary Excellence
- 05/2023 Oberseminar algebraische Geometrie (Saarbruecken, GER) Title: F-Theory and Singular Elliptic Fibrations
- 10/2020 Philadelphia, USA
  Title: Machine Learning and Algebraic Approaches towards Complete Matter Spectra in 4d F-theory
- o6/2020 Summer Series on String Phenomenology (Virtual)
  Title: On Stratification Diagrams, Algorithmic Spectrum Estimates and Vector-Like Pairs in F-theory
- 12/2019 Philadelphia, USA Title: From F-theory Standard Models to Freyd Categories and back
- 10/2018 Brussels, BE
  Title: Counting Massless Matter in F-theory with CAP
- 08/2018 *CAP\_days 2018* (Siegen, GER)
  Title: CAP, *Machine Learning and String Theory*
- o7/2014 Aachen, GER
  Title: The Standard Model from String Theory

#### Other Talks at Conferences, Workshops etc. (15)

- o6/2024 StringPheno 2024 (Pardova, IT)
  Title: Efficiency in F-Theory: FTheoryTools
- o7/2023 StringMath 2023 (Melbourne, AU)
  Title: Root bundles: Applications to F-theory Standard Models
- o7/2023 StringPheno 2023 (Daejeon, KR)
  Title: Root bundles: Applications to F-theory Standard Models
- o5/2023 Computeralgebra Tagung 2023 (Hannover, GER)
  Title: F-Theory Tools: String theory Applications of OCSAR
- 07/2022 String Math 2022 (Warsaw, PL) Title: Towards F-theory MSSMs
- 07/2022 String Pheno 2022 (Liverpool, UK) Title: Towards F-theory MSSMs
- 09/2021 Summer Series on String Phenomenology (virtual meeting)
  Title: Root Bundles and Towards Exact Matter Spectra of F-theory MSSMs
- 12/2020 *String Data 2020* (virtual conference)
  Title: *Vector-like spectra in F-theory* (joined with M. Liu)
- 08/2019 Gap Singular Meeting and School (Lambrecht, GER)
  Title: Monoidal Structures in Freyd Categories
- 05/2018 Seminar on *Holography and Large-N duality* (Heidelberg, GER)

Title: Conformal Invariants; Fefferman–Graham Expansion; Graham–Lee Theorem (with M. Zikidis) String Pheno 2017 (Virginia, USA) 07/2017 Title: Zero Mode Counting in F-Theory via CAP GAP Days (Aachen, GER) 08/2014 Title: String Theory, Sheaf Cohomology and the homalg Package Seminar Series What is? (Heidelberg, GER) 05/2014 Title: What is a Fermion/Boson (in Quantum Mechanics)? Heidelberg, GER 02/2014 Title: Cohomology of Holomorphic Pullback Line Bundles on Smooth, Compact Normal Toric Varieties Heidelberg, GER 05/2012 Title: Intersecting D6-Brane Models Posters at Conferences, Workshops etc. (2) StringMath 2023 (Melbourne, AU) 07/2023 Title: FTheoryTools – A Computer Tool for Singular Elliptic Fibrations Strings and Geometry (Oxford, UK) 09/2019 Title: Tensor Products of Finitely Presented Functors

## Conferences attended without Talk or Poster Contribution (17)

07/2022 Strings 2022 (Vienna, AT) 06/2022 Simons Collab.: Geometry, Topology and Singular Special Holonomy Spaces (Freiburg, GER) Simons Collab. (Homological Mirror Symmetry) Annual Meeting (New York, USA) 11/2021 Simons Collab.: Progress and Open Problems (Stony Brook, USA) 09/2021 Simons Collab. (Special Holonomy in Geometry, Analysis, Phys.) Annual Meeting (New York, USA) 09/2021 07/2021 String Pheno 2021 (virtual conference) Strings 2021 (virtual conference) 06/2021 String Math 2021 (virtual conference) 06/2021 String Pheno 2020 (virtual conference) 06/2020 Strings 2019 (Brussels, BE) 07/2019 03/2018 String Data 2018 (Munich, GER) 12/2015 String Math 2015 (Sanya, CN) Third GAP Days (Trondheim, NO) 09/2015 Second GAP Days (Aachen, GER) 03/2015 *Physics and Geometry of F-Theory* (Munich, GER) 02/2015 Homological Perturbation Theory (Galway, IE) 12/2014 02/2014 Geometry and Physics of String Compactifications (Heidelberg, GER)

# TEACHING RECORD

# Autonomous Instruction of Lecture Courses

Period	Title	University	Students	Weekly Teaching	Evaluation
04/2024 - 07/2024	Introduction to Topology	RPTU KL-LD, GER	5	$1 \times 1.5$ hours	Insufficient data due to sharp drop in RPTU KL-LD student numbers.
0I/2022 - 05/2022	Computational Linear Algebra	University Of Pennsylvania, USA	29	$2 \times 1.5 \text{ hours}$	2.12
0I/202I - 05/202I	Computational Linear Algebra	University Of Pennsylvania, USA	57	$2 \times 1.5 \text{ hours}$	2.04

Scale: Poor (0), Fair (1), Good (2), Very good (3), Excellent (4).

# Senior Teaching Assistant

Period	Title	University	Students	Weekly Teaching
10/2023 – current	Algebraic Geometry	RPTU KL-LD, GER	6	$1 \times 1.5$ hours
04/2018 - 10/2018	Methods of Math. Phys.	Heidelberg University, GER	51	$1 \times 1.5$ hours
04/2016 - 09/2016	General Relativity	Heidelberg University, GER	132	$1 \times 1.5  \mathrm{hours}$

# Teaching Assistant

Period	Title	University	Weekly Teaching
10/2016 - 03/2017	Theoretical Physics I	Heidelberg University, GER	$1 \times 1.5$ hours
04/2015 - 09/2015	Theoretical Physics IV	Heidelberg University, GER	$1 \times 1.5  \mathrm{hours}$
10/2014 - 03/2015	Quantum Field Theory	Heidelberg University, GER	$1 \times 1.5  \mathrm{hours}$
10/2013 - 03/2014	Theoretical Physics III	Heidelberg University, GER	$1 \times 1.5  \mathrm{hours}$
04/2013 - 09/2013	Theoretical Physics II	Heidelberg University, GER	$1 \times 1.5$ hours
10/2012 - 03/2013	Theoretical Physics I	Heidelberg University, GER	$1 \times 1.5  \mathrm{hours}$

#### REFERENCES

Prof. Dr. Mirjam Cvetič

POSITION Fay R. and Eugene L. Langberg Professor EMPLOYER Department of Physics and Astronomy

University of Pennsylvania, USA

EMAIL cvetic@physics.upenn.edu

PHONE +1 (215) 898 8153

Prof. Dr. Ron Donagi

POSITION Thomas A. Scott Professor of Mathematics

EMPLOYER Department of Mathematics

University of Pennsylvania, USA

EMAIL donagi@math.upenn.edu

PHONE +1 (215) 898 8465

Prof. Dr. Max Horn

POSITION Professor

EMPLOYER Department of Mathematics

RPTU Kaiserslautern-Landau, GER

EMAIL mhorn@rptu.de PHONE +49 631 205 2730